what is the Network+ certification
let's go ahead and find out
hey everybody this is Zach with IT career questions
and today we are answering what is the Network+ certification
if you haven't checked out the A+ certification video
go ahead and click on this link somewhere around here
and it was our previous video about answering CompTIA certification questions
this video specifically targets the Network+ certification
what is it what do I need to know about it why am I going to take it
so the Network+ certification again is a certification that is brought to you by CompTIA
you check out CompTIA or I'll put that link in the description below
the Network+ certification is an excellent certification to get
if you are looking to get some type of networking position
if you don't have a broad knowledge base of networking
or even if you do have a broad knowledge base of networking
if you're looking for that networking job
you might want to look at getting your network plus certification
definitely is a go-to as far as networking certifications go
and if you don't have a degree
you can definitely fall back on a network plus certification
because it is pretty good
and of course once you do the Network+ certification
you can go off and get your CCNA and all those things
you don't have to have a college degree to get any of these certifications
which is definitely very excellent if that's not the route that you took
even if you do have a college degree
it's still suggested that you get some of these certifications
because employers love to see that stuff
anyway the Network+ certification covers everything
networking right switches VLANs land lands access points
whatever it is that has to do with networking
you will learn with the Network+ certification
as i talked about in my previous video
if you are looking for lots of great information
and want to learn more about the Network+ certifications
go ahead and check out professor masters youtube channel
he has lots of great material over there
and he will give you lots of great examples
of how the Network+ certification tests are laid out
and basically goes start to finish with all that stuff
so check him out for now I can give you guys a couple of examples of Network+ certifications
that you may receive on the test
again keep in mind
there are so many questions to this test
that no test is exactly the same
it's not entirely true but there's so many different versions of the test
that you will take that you know they just mix up the questions and things like that
so a couple questions here I'm going to do three of them
one is a user's remote marketing server has changed IP address schemes
and now the user can no longer access it the user
the user for further discovers that the distant
and still has access to them
which of the following is a possible cause
so again this is all multiple choice
so A is SNMP strings need to be added
B firewall rules need to be configured
C port bonding on the interface needs to be enabled
D the switch has lost power
so multiple choice what would you go with
if you said B firewall rules need to be configured
that's the right answer so something
happened with the firewall
where it lost configuration
maybe nobody ever configured it
so you're gonna have to go ahead and configure that firewall
and see how that needs to be set up
in order for this user to access the marketing server
the next question is which of the following is a network device
that allows remote users access to a network
A DNS server
B content filter
C load balancer
D VPN concentrator
so based off this multiple choice question
I know the answer do you know the answer
if you said D VPN concentrator
that's correct you will use a VPN connection to remotely access your work Business Network
so that's second example of a network plus certification question
that you could receive on the test
that you may go out and take
third and last question that we'll go over is a technician suspects
that a virus has been introduced on the network
which network resources is best used to confirm this problem
A syslog
B SNMP
C network sniffer
and D environmental monitor
if you said C network sniffer you're right
you are going to use this tool to basically sniff out any problems
that you may have on the network
so these are the three examples that I gave you on
questions that you may receive on the Network+ certification test
the Network+ certification test is a great thing to study for
because it really does give you a broad example of how an entire network works
it starts you from the very beginning until almost towards the end
it's not going to go too far into the security things
and and how a lot of more complex things are set up
so don't go and take a network plus certification test
and expect that you're going to be like a network administrator right off the bat
that's probably not going to happen
you definitely have to get years of experience
on basically how networks are actually set up
you know every business is completely different from one another
every business uses completely different equipment sometimes
you know you might have HP curse
which is you might have Cisco switches
who knows
so you might need to know how each different brand configures their switches
and how all that stuff works
so again Network+ certification great thing to study for
again I kind of talked about this in the previous video on the A+ certification
you should actually also get your A+ certification
because that's really going to give you a strong backbone of computers
and a little bit of networking but it's a really powerful thing that you should learn
because it's lots of knowledge
and if you are not familiar with how computers and networks and all that stuff works
or you're not too comfortable with it
these are two really good tests that you guys can take and get certified for
and you guys will become employable
right after you do that test you are almost able to go out and get a job right away
just based off those certifications
people love to see these certifications
they really say oh this person does actually know a lot about network
they went out and got their Network+ certification
that's not an easy that's not an easy certification to get by any means
because there's a lot of studying involved and you need to know lots of things
and that's mainly because the test that you're going to take
could be completely different the next time that you were to take it
so you failed the first test and you go to take the next test
like man I remembered all the questions that I failed on this first test
then you go to this to take the second test over again right
questions are completely different
every single one is completely different
so just you know if you're looking to get a certification the Network+ certification specifically
do your studying go check out professor Messer great resource
to learn a lot about the Network+ and just networking in general
so I hope this answers part of the question about the Network+ certification
I will go into broader detail and actually show you guys examples
in the future as you guys know I'm working on the server setup
and I haven't had time to do a lot of those videos
I apologize for that
but I will be trying to get as many of those videos put out as I possibly can
it's really hard to do those videos
because they do take a lot of time to do
but bear with me I will get to them just as I will get to you more networking videos
and how you can set up a switch and how you can set up a VLAN and all that fun stuff
so you guys have any questions you know what to do
hit me up in the comments below
be more than happy to chat with you about anything you guys have questions about
as always you can leave me a question and I can answer it in the video
just like I'm doing right now
thank you guys so much for watching take it easy