ladies and gentlemen
please welcome judith bishop
good afternoon everybody
welcome back to the plenary session of the Microsoft faculty summit
it's my great pleasure to introduce to you today
Leslie Lamport who's a principal researcher at our Microsoft Research Silicon Valley Lab
so students and faculty who have taught operating systems courses
as well as anybody who's really used a computer
will have benefited from Leslie's work
on logical clocks 、safety and liveness 、sequential consistency
and many other parts of operating systems
which laid the basis for the safe operation of the computers that we have today
as they moved from the single desktop to the large number of interconnected devices we have
Leslie before he joined Microsoft was a member of certain various prestigious institutions
he was at MIT 、at Brandis University and at companies such as Dec 、Compaq and SR I
in his career he has also received several honorary doctorates
and he has tried very hard to help scientists see their works’s beautiful
and for that purpose he also developed something
that I think you all know very well which is let ik
he's now going to go on and try and persuade engineers
that there's something else that is beautiful in life
which is mathematics and
that's what he's going to talk to us about today
so ladies and gentlemen please put your hands together
for this year's am Turing Award winner
Leslie Lamport
Thank You Judith
thinking above the code
why do we think
well it helps us do most things
like hunting a saber-toothed tiger or building a house or writing a program
so when should we think
well hunting a saber-toothed tiger we should think before leaving the cave
when the tiger is charging at you
it's a little late
building a house before beginning construction
you don't want to think about what you're doing
when the Carpenters are putting the roof on
allready start thinking about what you're doing
writing a program we should be thinking before we start writing any code
how to think
when I favorite quotes is from the cartoonist Guindon
who says writing is nature's way of letting you know how sloppy your thinking is
to think to really think you have to write
if you're thinking without writing
chances are you're fooling yourself
we're only pretending to think
what to write？
well hunting a saber-toothed tiger
writing wasn't invented then which meant it was a very dangerous activity
building a house
well what'd you write before you build to start building a house are called blueprints
and it's called drawing blueprints
writing a program
well you should also write a blueprint of your program
but blueprints of programs are what we call specifications
specifications
well when I say the word people tend to panic
this formal stuff that's impossible to read and understand
and you have to learn these funny symbols and all that sort of stuff
yeah this is a blueprint you know all these complicated stuff going on
but this is also a blueprint
in fact there's an entire spectrum of blueprints
ranging from very detailed complicated blueprints
which you need if you're building something that's very big and complicated
at the other end
they're just rough sketch of what you're building is just something you know really simple
that you're gonna do in the weekend
and there are these ordinary blueprints for
you know things like a house or the stuff
that kinds of blueprints that most of us might have seen
and similarly there's a spectrum of specifications
there are formal specifications
and on the other end of the your formal specifications
written in a in a precise formal language
and on the other end there are just short prose specifications
and in the middle are what I like to call mathematical prose
most code is really simple few sentences of prose will do
some code is subtle will requires more thought
and for that you have to write it ’s prose but it's it try to be you need to be pretty precise
and some code is either very complex or very subtle or critical
and that's especially the case if what you're doing
is writing concurrent or distributed system
it is going to be complex and subtle and quite likely critical
and for that you should have tools
you should be using tools
to check it to check your blueprints
and if you're going to use tools it means you need a formal language
because tools don't understand prose
so how to write a spec
well writing requires thinking
so how to think about programs
we should think about programs like computer scientists namely like scientists
scientific thinking is a very successful way of thinking we know all that it's brought us
what science does is make mathematical models of reality
for example the first very successful science was astronomy
the reality planets have mountains oceans tides and weather
and all sorts of complicating things
but the simple model that's gotten astronomy pretty far
is to think of a planet model the planet as a point mass having position and momentum
computer science the reality consists of digital systems
things like a processor chip 、a game console or a computer executing a program
this is what I'll be talking about computer is executing programs
but what I have to say applies to all those other things just as well
so models there are lots of models that you've probably come across
Turing machines partially ordered set of events you probably haven't run across that
and lots of models but - to my mind stand out as being the most useful basic models
functions and sequences of states
so functions we model a function of a we can model a program as a function
that map's an input or to an output
or multiple inputs - or possible inputs to possible outputs
in math the function is very simple
it's an order as a set of ordered pairs
so for example the square function on natural numbers
it's this set of ordered pairs this pair 0-> 0 、1-> 1 、2-> 4 etc
and the element 2-> 4 is an element of this set of the fact that the outlet that
the pair 2-> 4 is an element of this square function is usually expressed
by saying square of 2 equals 4
now the domain of of square the domain of a function are all the first elements of those pairs
so for the square function the domain is the set number 0 1 2 & 3 etc
also known as the natural numbers that I like to write as n
to specify to define a function what you do is you specify its domain
so to specify square we say the domain of square is equal to the set of Naturals
and for each element X in its domain
we specify what Square maps X to
and it maps the value X to x squared
so that defines the square function
now functions in math are not the same as functions in programming languages
math is much simpler
I'm not a programming language expert
so I don't know what those things that programming languages
which is called functions are
but I know what math is that methods are a lot simpler
now the functions model will take you very far it's very useful
but there has limitations
its limitation main limitation is that it specifies what a program does but not how it does it
so for example quick sort and bubble sort compute the same function
but they're very different programs
also some programs don't just map inputs to outputs
some programs run forever well you know they may stop
before the the Sun explodes but it's useful to think of them it's running forever
for example operating systems you can't specify an operating system as a function
because it doesn't map inputs to outputs
so for that for those specifications use what I like to call
the standard behavioral model
in which a program execution is represented by a behavior
a behavior is a sequence of states
and a state is an assignment of values to variables
and a program is modeled by a set of behaviors
which behaviors that represent all possible executions of the program
so for example let's look at Euclid's algorithm
an algorithm is just an abstract program
as you all undoubtedly know
it computes the greatest common divisor of two natural of two integers m and n
by initializing x to m and y to m
and then it keeps subtracting the smaller from the larger
and when x and y are equal then it stops
because that x and y equals the GCD of M and n
so for M = 12 and N = 18 there's just one possible behavior
it starts with a state in which that assigns 12 to X and 18 to Y
and then subtract the next state is obtained by
subtracting the smaller one from the larger X from Y
so you get reach a state where x equals 12 and y equals 18 minus 12 or 6
and in the next state you subtract the smaller which is y from the larger and you wind up in the state
in which x equals 6 and y equals 6
and since x and y are equal you stop
so it's very simple algorithm
it has just one possible behavior
so how do we describe a set of behaviors
well first of all there's a theorem
that says any set B of behaviors
is the conjunct the intersection of two sets
a set of behaviors satisfying a safety property
and a set of behaviors satisfying a liveness property
so what our safety and liveness
well I'm not going to bother going into you know
the formal definitions but a safety property is false if and only if
it can be violated at some point during the behavior
so partial correctness is an example
partial correctness is violated if the program stops with the wrong answer
so that's some point in the behavior
you can tell that it that it the property was violated
the point at which the program stopped with the incorrect answer
the liveness property is one
in which you need to see the complete behavior in order to know if it's false
or if it's not satisfied by the by the program
classic example is termination
you can't tell that the program hasn't terminated
by looking at any finite piece of the program
you have to look at the entire behavior to know that it never terminates
so we satisfy specify a set of behaviors with by specifying a
safety property and aliveness property
now in practice specifying safety just turns out to be more important
because that's where errors are most likely to occur and tend to be more subtle
I mean liveness is important just not as important to safety
and so to save time I'm going to ignore aliveness today
and just talk about safety
so how to specify a safety property
we specify it with two things
the set of possible initial States
and the next state relation
which describes all possible successor states
of any state so what language should we use to write these things
well let's act like scientists
what language do mathema two scientists use
and the language is mathematics
that's the language of science
so the set of initial states they're described by a formula
so in Euclid's algorithm the set of initial States we initialize the initial state is one
in which X = M and Y = N
so that is specified that initial state is specified by this formula
and the only part this has only one it's only one possible initial state that satisfies that formula
the next state relation is also described by a formula
and to describe it
I'll use unprimed variables to talk about the current state or the first state of the pair
and prime variables we're talking about the next state
so let's look at the next state relation for Euclid's algorithm
there are two possibilities
either X is greater than Y or Y is greater than X
so that formula is going to be the
disjunction of two of two formulas
if X is greater than Y then the new value of x prime
is equal to what you get by subtracting Y from it
so it's new value of x prime is equal to the old value of
X minus the old value of y
and the new value of X of Y is equal to the old value
so that first formula is specified by all pairs of states satisfying X
greater than Y and in the initial state
in first state X prime equals x minus y
and y prime equals y were okay
you understand what what I said
and that describes one one possibility
or the disjunction of these formulas to the other case
it's or what Y is greater than X in the first state
and the value of y the new state and the value of y in the old state minus
the value of x in the old state etc
so this simple formula describes the next state ratio relation of Euclid's algorithm
so let's see how it works
how you get behaviors out of those two formulas
well for example for an example I'll take em equal to 12 and N equals 18
so to get the initial state we look at the initial predicate s-- predicate
and we substitute 12 for m and 18 for n
for what for n rather and you see you under
that substitution there's only one pair of values x and y that satisfy this
relation x equals 12 and y equals 18
so to get the next state the second state
we apply the next state look formula
substituting 12 for x and 18 for y
and we do that notice that 12 greater than 18 is false and 18 greater than 12 is true
we'll false and anything is false so that first half of the formula is false
true in anything is people to the rest of the formula
so this formula is satisfied by the old value of x being 12
and the new value of x being 18 minus 12 or 6
so this is the only possible next state that satisfies this next relation
when for the initial state x equals 12 and y equals 18
okay to find the next state we do the same thing we
substitute 12 for X and wife and 6 for y
we simplify we see that 6 greater than 12 is false and 12 greater than 6 is true
so the formula simplifies to x prime equals 12 minus 6 and y prime equals 6
so it tells us that the only possible successor state
the only possible third state is x equals 6 and y equals 6 and to find the next state
well do the same thing we substitute 6 for X and 6 for y and we see
that the entire formula is false
and there are no values of x prime and y prime which can make the formula false true
so there is no next state
so there's no next state means the program is stopped
so that's Euclid's algorithm
and when we see special about Euclid's algorithm is for any values of x and y
there are unique values of x prime and y prime
that make next true
there's either one value or no values
so Euclid's algorithm is deterministic
to model their non determinism
we just have a next state relation
that allows multiple next States for a current state
there's nothing magic you know terribly difficult
you know hard about can about non determinism
multiple assignments of values to prime variables
that make next true for a single assignment of values to unprimed variables
that's what non determinism is all about
okay what about formal specs
we need formal specifications only to apply tools
we mathematicians you know before there were any tools you know wrote math
you know very you know an informal notation
they want to use Mathematica though they have to you know write in the language Mathematica
so if we want to apply of tools we need a formal language
and the language that I'm going to describe were
I use is called TLA plus
so this this pair of formulas are written just like this in TLA plus
we need to form a language we need to write declarations
we declare m and n to be constants and x and y to be variables
and then add a little boilerplate we said it extends the integers
the integer or a standard module that defines things like plus and minus and greater than
and we put them inside of a module which I've called module Euclid
and that's a TL A+ specification of Euclid's algorithm
and this is what it looks like in SK
now you can model check TLA plus specs
know model checking conceptually checks all possible confusions of the program on a very small model
it's extremely effective and quite easy to do
you know you basically tell the model checker what the model is
models are usually you know instantiating values of constants
so for Euclid's algorithm we'd have to tell it what m and n equals
and then the model checker will go through
and in you know a few nanoseconds
for something that simple will we'll check whoa b1 possible
their behavior and you can write formal correctness proofs
and check them mechanically in TLA
you know write the proofs in TLA plus
and we have a theorem prover that can check the proofs
and that's hard work and well all this is math stuff
we know he's you know it's really very well nice and pretty stuff
but we know that math works only for toy examples
to model real system you need a real language
with types procedures objects and all of that
ma'am wrong let me quote something written by Chris Newcomb as an Amazon engineer
said we have used TL A+ on 10 large complex real-world systems
in every case TL A+ has added significant value
either preventing subtle serious bugs from reaching production
or giving us enough understanding and confidence
to make aggressive performance optimizations without sacrificing correctness
one of the other things people will tell you about formal methods is
oh if you use a formal method you're really going to kill your performance
well in fact it's just the opposite
and the other thing they'll tell you is Oh management will never let us do it
well management at Amazon and now encouraging teams to write TL a-plus specs
and in annual planning managers are allocating engineering time to use TLA Plus
this was written in 2013 I think there are a few more systems
that they've been specifying since then
the xbox360 memory system
a Chuck Thacker had an intern right at TLA plus spec of the Xbox memory system
and just writing the spec didn't even get to point of model checking it
he caught a bug that the designers of the memory system at IBM
after scratching their heads looking at it said yeah that was a bug
and that would not have been caught by their testing procedures
and that bug would have caused every Xbox in the world to crash after four hours of use
you can learn about TLA plus on the web
today I'm not going to be talking about TLA plus
I'm going to be talking about informal specifications
and I'll start with an example
TLA Tech which is the pretty printer for TL A+
here is what somebody user TL A+ user might write
some silly formula like this
and if you just did the naive output
just took things from teletype font and put them into translated the ascii into the symbols
left / right / into the conjunction symbol
and you get something like that formula and the right
but alignment is actually has significance in TL a-plus
and the user undoubtedly wanted he certainly wanted the left conjunction symbols aligned
because the formula might mean something different otherwise
and he also probably wanted those equal signs aligned
so this is the right output that the pretty partition produce for this example
on the other hand if you look at this input
this is what the naive output would be like
and the user probably didn't want those two symbols aligned
that was probably just an accidental
so in this case the naive output is the correct output that's what you want
well there's no precise definition of correct alignment
correctness means what the user wants
and there's no way of formally specifying what the user wants
so obviously if we can specify correctness specification
what good can specification we need to specify correctness
what could how can we use specification
well we can
not knowing what a program should do doesn't mean you don't have to think you just do this code
it means you have to think a lot harder
which means that that's what a spec is even more important
when you don't know what the program is supposed to do
and it seems impossible to even say what it should do
because it has to do something and you have to decide what it should do
so that requires a lot of thinking which requires writing
so what did I do
well my spec consisted of six rules plus definitions
and these are in informal met you know quote mathematical prose
and formal if they're written in comments
oh here's an example of one of the rules
it says a left comment token is left comment aligned with its covering token
well I don't even know what that means anymore
I'd have to read the spec
but left comment aligned and covering token are terms
that were defined in the in this specification I wrote
and if you look at it this is really mathematical prose
what did I write this spec well it was a lot easier to understand and debug six rules
than 850 lines of code probably would have been more than 850 lines of code
if I hadn't written those rules first
and I did a lot of debugging of the rules
you know you write a bunch of rules
and you know what they're going to do is not obvious
and you try a bunch of examples and I a debugging code
so I could see what rules were being applied
and we don't would do with something weird and I say oh and that rule needs to be modified
for this and an iterative process
and the few bugs and implementing the rules were easy to catch
though there was no problem
had I just written the code
it would have taken me much longer to just get something I could live with
and I'm sure the results wouldn't have produced formatting nearly as good
so why not a formal spec why didn't I write at TLA + spec
well several reasons
first of all getting it right was not that important
the world is not going to come crashing
down if something isn't quite properly aligned and pretty printing
in particular it didn't have to work in all corner cases
yes No you know there's no way of getting it you know totally right
and just as important there aren't any tools
that could help me the model checker wouldn't have helped in this example
because you know you need some some properties to check it against
and you know they're just tools were not
you know the TLA plus tools are not designed for that kind of problems
so what's typical about this spec
the spec is at a higher level than the code
it could have been implemented in any language
no method nor tool none of your favorite ways of you know programming methodologies
would have been worth a damn here
they would not have helped me write the spec
because no method of writing you know better code
would have made the spec unnecessary
I had to write the spec it was not code
and it says nothing about how to write the code you could implement my spec in any language
you write a spec to help you think about the problem before you think about the code
so what's not typical about this spec
it's quite subtle
remember I said 95% of code people write requires less thought
and you know simpler shorter specs good enough
also it's a set of rules
a set of rules or requirements or axioms is usually a bad spec
because it's really hard to understand
it turns out that that was a good match for this particular problem
which says there are no universal rules about how to write specs
no universal rules that'll tell you how to write any program in the world
so specifying how to compute a function
specifying what the pretty printer should do is hard
implementing the spec was easy
specifying what a sorting program should do is easy
figuring out how to implement it efficiently is hard
at least if nobody has showed you how
it requires thinking which requires writing a specification
so I'll give you an example of a specification for quicksort
probably you all seen quicksort
quicksort is written by Tony Hoare it's a divide-and-conquer algorithm
for sorting an array
call it a zero to a n minus one
and for simplicity I'll assume that's an array of numbers
and it uses a partition procedure you give it two arguments low and high
and what that procedure does is it chooses a pivot point
pivot number in low to high minus 1
and then it permutes the elements to the left of the pivot a low to a high
it permutes the number the the part of the array within the limit from low to high
so that everything from pivot downwards
is becomes is less than or equal to
everything from pivot plus 1 upwards
so fortunately if well seen quick sort before
so i rambling description isn't necessary
and for this example I don't care how this procedure is implemented
of course that's the real trick of quicksort implementing
that but you know I only have 50 minutes here so
so let's specify quicksort and pseudocode
you know this by the partition procedure is pick a pivot and low-to-high -1 and
permute a low to a high to make bla bla
bla and return the value pivot
and you have a recursive procedure q s applied to low to high
and if low is less than high
you call the protection procedure for on low and high
and then you recursively call the procedure for the 2 subintervals
and if low is not less than high then it means you have one element
and there's nothing to sort and so you're done
and the main program just implies Q s to the entire array from Sirte and minus one
so informal no formal syntax no declarations pseudocode
it's it's a fine specification yeah when
you're gonna code you know pretty trivial to code from this
and you know any programming language
easy to understand
but it's a really quick sort
it's the way quicksort is almost always described
but recursion is not a form fundamental part of quicksort
it's just one way of implementing divide and conquer
now here's a problem
and in fact it's probably not the best way
if you want to execute this on multiple cores
so here's a problem give to your friends and colleagues
write a non recursive version of quicksort
almost no one can do it in ten minutes
they try to compile the recursive version
and nobody can get
almost nobody can get that right and ten minutes standing on their feet
but I'll tell you you know what the real solution is
we do is maintain a set u of index ranges
on which partition needs to be called
initially u equals contain is a set containing a single index range
from zero and minus one represented by this pair
now we can write this in pseudocode
but let's be scientists let's write init and next directly in mathematics
so the initial predicate
says a is equal to any array of numbers of length n
and u is equal to the set consisting of that single element
yep this is in formal mathematics but it's informal you know
we could write some formal way of describing the set of a on any array of numbers of length N
and before writing next let me make a definition
let me define partitions of B pivot low high
it's the set of arrays obtained from B
by permuting the load to be high
with pivot point pivot in other words
it's the set of all values that the partition procedure
the set of all new values of a that
the partition procedure is allowed to return
if it's also returning pivot as the pivot point
and I won't bother writing it out precisely
so next remember it's going to be a relation between the old values of a of U
and the new values a prime and u Prime
so let's write it
first of all we're gonna stop
if u is the empty set
so the next state relation says U is not equal to the empty set
and so performing there's going to be false if u is the empty set
then we pick any pair BT in U and if B
is not equal to T then we pick any point P any number P lying in B to t minus 1
and we let a prime be any element of
the set of legal partitions you know the
results of the partition function that
if you've given it B and T is the input
and it returns P as the partition as the
pivot point and then u prime is a set u
we're finished with the remain element bT
so we move that from the set and then we add the 2 subintervals
be P and you know to be and P plus 1 to T
into the set u of of ranges that still need to be sorted
otherwise if B is not e is equal to T then there's nothing to do
we leave a prime unchanged and we let u prime equal u with BT removed
we just take BT out of out of the set
and that's the next state relation
that describes a very nice way of doing quicksort iterative iteratively
it's actually a more general algorithm because if you
look at all the behaviors that can produce
the set of behaviors produced by the recursive version is a sub set
that is the set of all sequences of values
that a assumes is going to be a subset
of the ones that this next state relation allows
so why can almost no one find this version of quicksort
because people's minds are stuck in code
they haven't thought learn to think at a higher level than the code
now it's easy to write this as a precise formula
pick any arbitrary value is really existential quantification
the formula is true if there exists a value B T and u similarly there
and just let letting a prime be any element of this set
well that's easy enough to write
is a prime and an element of that
and those relations new values of U prime those thinks the
with prose to the right of the equal sign
they're easy to express
whoops this way and so on then
so what you have is a TLA plus formula here perfectly formal
if you prefer pseudocode
we have plus Cal it looks like a toy programming language
and the algorithm in fact appears in a comment and TLA plus module but an expression
can be any TLA plus expression
it also has some constructs for non determinism
but the fact that it can be any TLA
an expression can be any TLA plus expression
which means any expression of mathematics
makes it enormously powerful more more expressive than
anything any programming language designer has ever dreamed of
and it gets compiled to an easy-to-understand TLA plus spec
and in fact I regularly write things in plus cal
and then when I'm proving the correctness of them
I reason directly about the TLA plus specification
and you like the TLA plus tools the model checker
and theorem prover to the plus to the translation
programs that run forever have been talking about programs that compute a function
programs that run forever usually involve concurrency
things like operating systems distributed systems
few people can get them right
by just thinking and writing
I'm not one of them
we need tools to check what we're doing
the reason the TLA plus was so useful to the Amazon engineers is
because the model checker
so for concurrent and distributed systems you need to write something
you use TLA plus or plus Cal it was designed for distributed systems
it's great and you're not gonna get it you know distributed concurrent algorithm right
if you don't model check
it it's spent you don't write a specification and check it
the other 95% really simple stuff here is an example
of a spec you know that I write wrote in a program
why did I write that spec
to be sure I knew what the code should do before writing it
without writing aspect I only thought it was obvious what it should do
I had to write the spec to be sure it was really as simple and as obvious
as I thought it was
and later I didn't have to read the code
to know what that piece of code I wrote did
I just wrote the specification could read the specification
so a general rule that's one rule at least we can say about specs in general
if you're writing a spec of what a code should do
what a piece of code should do
that should say everything that anyone needs to know to use the code
how the code worked in the example I've just showed
was just too simple to require a spec
I mean it was it turned out to be harder than I thought
I would have discovered that when I started coding
and I would have stopped coding and wrote and written a specification
so what programmers should know about thinking
what everyone should know about thinking
everyone thinks they think
but if you don't write down your thoughts
you're fooling yourself
what programmers should know about thinking
is that you should think before you code
which means you should write before you code
a spec is simply what you write before coating
so what coach you know what do I mean by code what should you specify
basically any piece of code that someone else might want to use or modifying
and that somebody else is likely to be you in a month
when you've forgotten what this piece of code you've written does
it could be an entire program or system a class a method
just a tricky piece of code inside of a method
what should you specify about the code
what it does
which means everything anyone needs to know to use it
and perhaps how it does it
if it's complicated subtle you need to think hard about in order to get it right
this is you know what's sometimes called an algorithm
or a high-level design
how should you think about or specify your code above the code level
in terms of states and behaviors or
functions for input output relations
should do it mathematically
as rigorously informally as is necessary
you should be thinking mathematically
even if you're writing thing the mathematics very informally
perhaps with pseudocode or pass or plus Cal
if you're specifying how something does it
so how do you learn to write specs
by writing formal specs even if you don't
even if you never need to write a completely formal spec in your life
learning to write formal specs will really help you learn to write the informal specs
that you need to write
you learn to write programs by writing them running them and correcting your errors
you can learn to write formal specs by writing them running them
with a model checker and correcting your errors
now TL A+ may not be the best language for you
you know it's I'm sure it's not the best language for formal language
for every kind of specification in the world
no language can be
it may not be the best form of language you know for what your particular needs are
but I do know that it's great for
learning to think mathematically
so unless you can find something better for doing that you know which works use TL a plus
you know learn TL a plus
learn to think mathematically
how do you connect the spec to the code
well you have comments connecting mathematical concepts and their implementation
for example the mathematical concept might
be a graph
and the implementation would be an array of node objects and an array of link objects
in this connection the other specification especially
if it's an informal specification should be in the comments
and so should the explanation of how those mathematical
comments are implemented in the code
so what about coding
I mean we're programs involve writing code you have to write code
I have nothing to say about writing code
nothing I said implies anything
you still have to think while you code
which means you have to write while you're coding
but what you're right while you're coding is is code
and I have nothing to say about how you should code
use any programming language you want
any programming methodology
you still you're still going to have to test and debug your program
not this good writing aspect is we're going to catch coding errors
because it's not about coding
it'll catch algorithm errors
writing specs is an additional step
and it may save time by catching errors early
when they're easier to correct no promises there
it certainly will improve you programming
so you'll be writing better programs
why are programmers reluctant to write specs
well writing is hard writing is hard
in fact because thinking is hard
you know there's no Royal Road to mathematics
as who wasn't who said that Archimedes I think
why is writing hard well because writing requires thinking
and thinking is hard
and as I said it's easier to think you're thinking
writing is a lot like running
unless you do it slower you are
and you have to strengthen your writing muscles
you know just like you have to strengthen your rust
and you're running muscles it takes practice
and it's easier to find an excuse not to
and one of the nicest excuses well what if the spec is wrong
maybe you made a mistake in the spec
maybe the requirements change where
some enhancement is needed
in fact and the code will have to be changed maybe even before the program is finished
in fact changing the code is something that
eventually happens to all useful programs
your program is useful
it's gonna have users the users are going to find things extra things they want of it
the things that don't work the way
you know you thought was a good idea be your customers
you know decide otherwise this happens eventually happens to all useful programs
in an ideal world you'd write a new spec
and then you know the code you'd completely rewrite the spec of the spec
well we all know this isn't gonna happen
in the real world the code is patched
and if you're lucky the spec is updated
well if this is inevitable why bother writing specs in the first place
if you know this little lovely thing is
you know the spec turns out you know - has to be changed and you know
we're back in our old messy world
well there's two reasons
the first reason is that whoever has to modify the code
will be eternally grateful for every word or formula of specification that you write
and whoever maybe you believe me I've you've done that you know coming back
and don't have time for second stories
but particularly you know modifications and the pretty print or in fact
and that's why you should update the spec when you change the code
the second reason is that every time code is patched
it becomes a little uglier harder to understand and harder to maintain
and if you but if you don't start with a spec every piece of code you write
is a patch which means the program starts out from the beginning
being ugly hard to understand and hard
to maintain and then God help you when you do have to maintain
you know try to unfit out what it's doing in order to to
make changes as Dwight Eisenhower said
no battle was ever won according to plan
but no battle was ever won with that one
so some people will tell you that
writing specs is a waste of time
in some situations and maybe
sometimes there's no need to think about what you're doing maybe something is really so trivial
that you know doesn't need much thought
but we'll remember when they're telling you not to write a spec
they're telling really telling you not to think
and you know thinking is a really good idea
and don't trust anybody who tells you not to do it
thinking doesn't guarantee that you won't make mistakes
but not thinking generally guarantees that you will
find out more about TLA plus go to my home page and click on the link to the TLA web page
thank you
[Applause]
I think there's time for a few questions
very few I think
one yeah yes
I hope that's not a judgment on my talk
thanks for your talk
how about specification by example
it's a pragmatic approach that is a little bit inspired by test-driven development
which since it's not complete of course
but since completeness anyway is undecidable
it's a good pragmatic approach so do you know
so terrible pragmatic approach it's maybe a good
maybe a good way to explain what something examples are great to explain them
but they're terrible they keep you from thinking
you think in terms of these particular examples
the real problem in programming is not to think of your the easy cases the obvious cases
the nice case if the hard cases
and you don't get that with examples
and boy I'll tell you I used to eclipse programming
and I've you know there's so much so many methods of eclipse
that are explained by here's an here's an example of code using it
and I have yet to manage to use those methods to do it what I want to do
because it doesn't work I find that it just doesn't work on anything other than that example
and I have no idea why not
not a program you know programming by example
I don't know about you know if that works
but a specification by example it doesn't
thank you for the great talk um
so what happens once you patch the code
do you suggest keeping the old specs around or
do you just get rid of him
like does it help to have context
well first of all I think whenever I well whenever I do fix bugs and that may require changing the spec
I will also take a note as to why I change the spec
because you know two years later I'm going to come back
and say why did I do that
about whether you know to what extent that's useful
for the specification itself I don't know
certainly you're always a good idea not to throw anything away
you know we shouldn't be throwing you know information away these days you know
it doesn't cost anything to save it so you should certainly save the old specs
whether you should you know
whether you should mention the change in the
in the new spec I don't I don't have any
any good answer to that
without wanting to be rude or anything I think most programmers
don't use formal specifications anymore
my PhD was in that background
most programmers these days they take algorithms they take code
they adapt it to what they want to do
and that's 99 percent is from my perspective
how most software is built these days
that we actually really be nice if it
if that where it can build Bell built well that way
it doesn't work because they're trying to use
I find that it doesn't work because the other pieces of code
that I want to use don't have specifications
so I really can't use them very well
I do the best I can
and I wind up having to spend a hell of a lot of time
trying to figure out what this piece of code does
which something I shouldn't have to do if it had been specified
again I've said that you know 95% of programming
you know requires very little specification
and you know a few lines you know are usually enough
but you know you are going to come up with this 5%
which isn't just you know take this thing and put it here
and combine it with this thing
there's gonna be something some things code you're gonna have to write
that is subtle it has some some a bit of difficulty in it
and you want to be able to you know you want to be prepared for that
because we use the same techniques that
you use you're the same lack of thought
that you use when you're doing that other 95%
you're gonna screw up badly
unfortunately I have never really looked into TLA plus
but having studied temporal logic it is inevitable to to fail to to notice that
that there's a lot of temporal logic
going on underlying what you've been saying
so I was wondering have you studied probably you have the possibilities
for using more directly the language of temporal logic
will future operates as necessity operators and all that stuff and so
ok TLA stands for the temporal logic of actions
temporal logic is evil
I can tell you explain why because it's very hard to use
but it turns out it's a necessary evil
temporal logic turns out to be the best way of thinking about liveness
and so if you use TLA plus when you get to the liveness part you're
going to be using temporal logic and be aware of it
but remember that I said that safety is more important and it turns out that you do not need to think
you got not need to know temporal logic
in order to handle safety
and what the reason I think you know that TL A+ is better than other kinds of temporal logic
is that you need-to-know essentially no temporal logic to use it for safety
if you look at the actual specification
there is the specific the TLA specification I've noticed
I've written it it's two formulas in it and next
well TLA allows you to combine them into a single temporal logic formula
which you you know you do at the end eventually
and but the idea of the thing it makes it great is that
you'll write a thousand line specification 999 lines are going to be ordinary math
initial predicate next state relation and then the last line is going to be a temporal logic formula
so okay
well do we have no
so we are now at the end of our plenary session
and I'd like to thank you very much but before we do that
just to remind you all we got the buses outside to go out to the dinner tonight
take your bags with you there will be space there for your bags
and then we'll be going back to the hotels or coming back here and
now thank you very much Leslie
[Applause]