hey what's up guys this is gee here with kevin trainings
welcome to this quick video in which i'm going to respond to
a question that i receive here a lot on
kb trainings
as you know cable trainers i go from zero to engineer so most of you or some of you
are beginners in this industry in
networking in general
and you're asking yourself what are the
best books that you can read
as a beginner in networking what books can you read
to get you to master all the concept of networking
as you know here on kb trainings i share with you most of what i know and what i'm still learning in this field
so i'm a network professional
but if you've been on this channel for a while
you might have seen my video in which i talk about books
i talk about reading what i think in general is that
you should read of course
but i'm not a book guy
you know that book person who has a huge library behind him with all kind of books
it's kind of disappearing this is 2020
we have the internet we have a lot of things so i think
if you really want to read you don't need to invest into a lot of books
you should invest into something that
will make you know what you have to research on the internet
and you can pretty much read anything on google on many websites
and by the way on kb trainings i just started a blog
so i'm going to be uh writing articles in this blog here
if you go on the website and
you click blog um this is the first article like
most of the videos like every i mean not every
but most of the videos on this channel will be an article
this is the exact article in which i'm responding to this specific question about
the books that you can read i'm not saying that don't buy books
but you have the internet that's where you can read a lot
you can read most of the things on the internet
but if you have to buy a book or if you want to study
if you are a beginner
i'm going to advise you to get certified
you need to pick a certification a networking certification
and study for the cert and get the book for that specific certification
and at the end of the cert you have the knowledge
and your knowledge will be structured in your head
because if you are studying without any kind of plan or any kind of blueprint
you're uh going to be all over the place
there's a lot to learn in networking
so if you have a certification it's going to be much easier for you
so the two certifications that i'm recommending
first the comptia network plus
it's a very good one it's vendor neutral
it's good to get when you are getting your feet in the industry
i started with it and then i went to the ccna
and the second one you might have guessed is the ccna
so if you are studying for the network plus it will teach you a lot of concept of networking
and it's all going to be structured
for those two certifications if you want to get the books for network plus
let's go on amazon
if you do um network plus on amazon you get some books
and i can recommend any of these books
this one for example um
or this other one but i i'll give you a link um to to get a book for on network plus
and if you're looking for the ccna you can just um type ccna 200 301
and this is what you're going to get
yeah this is the the one that i prefer
and if you get this one you're going to study for your cert
and you will get certified after a few months of studies
and you also need to check out of course the official pages of these certifications
if you go on compia.com i mean comptia.org
you can see this is the official page for the network plus
it gives you the details about the exam
and if you fill out this form
and you submit it's going to send you
the exam objectives
and some practice questions for you to know exactly what it is
so personally i prefer the ccna because it's more practical practical
the network plus is vendor neutral so sometimes it's kind of hard to master some concept
because you don't have any vendor that you can practice on
but if you go with the ccna this is the blueprint for the ccna
if you just type ccna 300 um 201 i mean 200 301 blueprint
this is what you get uh it's right here
it's a pdf you have a list of topics or concepts that you have to know
before going and taking the exam
this is going to help you
this is going to uh just structure whatever you have to know
i also recommend to get some kind of training videos
i do videos myself on cabbagetrends.com if you are interested
but any um any trainer or any training company is able to train you
and walk you through the exam blueprint
until you master everything and you can go and take the exam
so that's uh that's what i can tell you
but again remember you have the biggest book in the world
you have the internet
you should know how to search the internet
you have youtube
you should go on youtube and watch people that are doing networking stuff
you yeah you have all those means of study
so today you can just be alone and be in your bedroom
but still get a lot of knowledge
because a lot of people are online just like me uh saying
i'm showing you what we do and showing you what is really necessary
in this world right now as a professional
so yeah that's it that's all i can tell you and
i'll be doing a lot of ask me anything type of video
so if you like this don't forget to leave the comment and like the video
subscribe if you if you are a tech guy and you like more of this
i will be coming with a lot of videos on the channel
so don't forget to do that for me and check out the blog
and if you have any comment
just put it down below and i'll be able to follow that
other than that thank you for watching and i'll see you in the next video bye